One Room School House Association
State University of New York at Oswego
One Room School House Association
1973 - 1980
The collection contains correspondence, organizational documents, background papers and newspaper clippings of the activities of the association. The collection also consists of original artifacts, photographs, and ephemera from the school.
2 boxes 2 linear feet
Jackim, Dr. Halas L.
State University of New York at Oswego Penfield Library 7060 State Route 104 Oswego, New York 13126-3599
2003.097.0001
Collection is open to the public.
The One Room School House Association was established to serve as an operating museum and learning center for the State University of New York, Oswego. The organization was formed in the early 1970’s and dissolved in the 1980’s, when the school was reconstructed and relocated.
One Room School House Association; Oswego City and County Tourist Information Center; Oswego (N.Y.); School buildings--New York (State); Jackim, Dr. Halas L.; Jackim, Lois; Dennler, Florence; Moss, Theodore; Education--History
The collection mainly consists of correspondences, newspaper clippings, and administrative records. Also included are original artifacts, photographs, a 45 star American flag, and ephemera from the school.
- Background Material (Box-folder 01-01)
  A postcard and various articles pertaining to one room schoolhouses
- Background Material, 1920 (Box-folder 01-02)
  A schedule that the school district used to adhere to, various articles pertinent to the one room schoolhouse, and a photograph c. 1920 of a class in a one room school house.
- Reports of trips to one room school houses, n.d. (Box-folder 01-03)
  Papers written by students visiting one room school houses. They include observations on the teaching style, lessons presented, etc.
- Oral history transcript of Ted Moss, n.d. (Box-folder 01-04)
  Oral transcript of Ted Moss, the first president of the One Room Schoolhouse Association at the Dept. of Education at SUNY Oswego.
- Photographs and slides (Box-folder 01-05)
  Various photographs and slides of the one room schoolhouse project.
- One Room Schoolhouse Association Papers, n.d. (Box-folder 01-06)
  Various papers by students and faculty pertaining to the One Room Schoolhouse Association, and the the one room schoolhouse movement.
- Newspaper Articles, n.d. (Box-folder 01-07)
  Newspaper articles about one room schoolhouses in general, and the restoration of the One Room Schoolhouse Association.
- Background Material (Box-folder 01-08)
  Articles written about one room schoolhouses.
- Background Material (Box-folder 01-09)
  Articles and a pamphlet by NAHO about one room schoolhouses/ early education
- Florence Dennler's notes on Oswego County Schools, n.d. (Box-folder 01-10)
  Information and correspondence researched and written by F. Dennler.
- Background Information (Box-folder 01-11)
  Information on School District No. 6
- Stationery, Envelopes, and Membership cards (Box-folder 01-12)
  Stationery, envelopes and membership cards all produced for the "One Room Schoolhouse Association of Oswego County, Inc."
- Building Plans, n.d. (Box-folder 01-13)
- Members, Trustees, n.d. (Box-folder 01=14)
  Membership cards and address list for members and trustees of the "One Room Schoolhouse Association of Oswego County, Inc."
- Employment, n.d. (Box-folder 01-15)
  Correspondence and employee records/evaluations concerning those employed in restoring the one room schoolhouse.
- Financial Documents, n.d. (Box-folder 01-16)
  Financial Documents Records, reciepts, correspondence, and insurance forms concerning the one room school house.
- Minutes and Announcements (Box-folder 01-17)
  Announcements and minutes of meetings for the committee of the One Room Schoolhouse of Oswego County, Inc.
- Incorporation papers, n.d. (Box-folder 01-18)
  Correspondence and legal documents about the incorporation of the One Room Schoolhouse of Oswego County committee.
- Legal Documents, n.d. (Box-folder 01-19)
  Legal documents concerning the One Room Schoolhouse Association of Oswego County, Inc
- Historic Preservation, n.d. (Box-folder 01-20)
  Documents pertaining to the filing of the one room school house as a historic building.
- Grants, n.d. (Box-folder 01-21)
  Correspondence, applications, pamphlets, etc. concerning grants applied for/granted to the One Room Schoolhouse Association of Oswego County, Inc.
- Correspondence, 1977 - 1984 (Box-folder 01-22)
  Correspondance written concerning the one room schoolhouse restoration
- Correspondence, 1975 - 1976 (Box-folder 01-23)
  Correspondence written to members and others concerning the one room schoolhouse
- Correspondence, 1973 - 1974 (Box-folder 01-24)
  Correspondence to members and others concerning the one room school house.
- Correspondence [n.d.] (Box-folder 01-25)
  Undated correspondence and documents concerning the one room school house committee.
- Correspondence, 1970 - 1971 (Box-folder 01-26)
  Correspondence concerning the One Room Schoolhouse project.
- Correspondence, 1972 (Box-folder 01-27)
- Minutes, articles, writings, 1975 (Box-folder 01-28)
  Various news articles, minutes of meetings, and writings about the One Room Schoolhouse project.
- One Room Schoolhouse Photographs, 1911 - 1974 (Box-folder 01-29)
  Seventeen photographs of one room schoolhouses. Black + white and color. Please see Photo Catalog records 2003.097.0002 to 2003.097.0010.
- One Room Schoolhouse Photographs and Slides, 1975 (Box-folder 01-30)
  One Room Schoolhouse Photographs and Slides Nine color and one black + white photograph of one room schoolhouse. Twelve color slides.
- American flag, 1896 - 1908 (02)
  45 star American flag. c. 1896 - 1908. 2 wooden rulers.